This video is sponsored by Short Form.
If you're looking to engage more with
the world's best non-fiction books, but
feel overwhelmed or limited by time,
Short Form makes reading more manageable
without diluting the ideas. Get a free
trial and $50 off your annual plan using
my link in the description.
There was a moment in time when you were
nothing more than a zygote. You're in
existence, [music] but as a mere cell,
determinably you, but spherical, smooth,
a gel-like droplet with no other
distinct features. Out of that, somehow,
hints of your arms, legs, torso, and
head began to grow. Slowly, at first,
then quickly. There was a moment in time
when you were nothing more than a fetus.
A soft, supple, and helpless arrangement
of gelatin-like flesh contained within
and dependent on the body of your
biological mother. You were alive but
not independent. Formed but far from
complete. As your body pushed and molded
into a defined state, details and
functions emerged. And soon you entered
the world, a suddenly independent thing,
no longer constrained inside a
biological womb. Now you were and still
are constrained inside the womb of human
existence. That is the nature of your
body and the world. Now you must
breathe, bleed, sweat, eat, defecate,
decay, die. If the thought of any of
that, the grotesque morbid nature of the
body and existence, unsettles you, you
are experiencing an intimation of a dark
and unsettling concept in philosophy
known as the object.
Objection.
In 1980, Bulgarian French philosopher,
literary critic, and psychoanalyst Julia
Cava published an essay titled Powers of
Horror. In it, she explores and defines
a comprehensive overview of the
psychological and philosophical concept
known as objection. Plainly, objection
is the visceral, uncanny, and
disconcerting experience of becoming
aware of the mechanisms of one's
selfhood and corporeality. More
specifically, it is the realization or
interfacing with what is typically
beyond the boundaries of what we
consciously deem acceptable and bearable
about ourselves and existence. It
reveals a threat posed by what we cannot
cleanly exclude from ourselves but wish
we could.
Fundamentally, we define and understand
ourselves by establishing borders
between who or what we are and aren't
both physically and abstractly. For
example, on a physical level, we define
ourselves by what's in and perhaps on
our body and not what is beyond [music]
it. Our border here is the edge of our
body. But of course, we also define
ourselves in abstract and conceptual
ways like through the character traits,
[music] preferences, values, and other
things we associate with and express.
Everything we conceptually reject,
loathe, or find appalling and wrong is
beyond this abstract and psychological
border and not us. We maintain our sense
of self through the maintenance and
order of these boundaries, [music]
preserving them by keeping everything
that we deem unacceptable or unappealing
out. According to Cava, however, along
with many other psychoanalytic and
phenomenological thinkers like Sigman
Freud and George Patai, our conscious
mind works to repress and deny many
qualities that are part of who or what
we are. We work to ignore, deny,
overcome, or repress things associated
with our flawed, fragile, caporeal, and
mortal condition. We avoid talk of
illness and death. We fill our days with
frivolous distractions. We hide our
vulnerabilities and fears. [music] We
measure ourselves in terms of
usefulness. And we paint over the terror
and madness of so much of what we are
and do. But in moments when we see, for
example, a corpse or our blood, vomit or
something rotting, we can be reminded of
the truth, the grotesque nature of our
being. In these moments of elucidation,
according to Cava, our clean, orderly
sense of self is suddenly damaged and
destabilized. We experience a loss of
distinction between ourselves and the
world, between subject and object. We
see the borders dissolve and we become
momentarily caught in a limbo between
our sense of self and other. Christa
writes, "Objection is above all
ambiguity [music] because while
releasing a hold, it does not radically
cut off the subject from what threatens
it. On the contrary, objection
acknowledges it to be in perpetual
danger. Our flesh, blood, vomit, feces
and skeleton. All of this is us, central
to us. [music] Objection reminds us of
this. The clean boundaries of normaly
and pleasantness are thin figments. And
so too is our sense of self and
stability.
Ultimately, whether we accept it or not,
we are also what we reject.
Missanthropy.
The concept of the object both brings up
questions about what we really are and
leads [music] us to answers that often
make us feel repugnant or gross. And if
we continue further into the limbo realm
of what we often are but repress, deny,
and repel, we also find unsettling
[music] vices and flaws. Our
wretchedness, selfishness, greed,
hypocrisy, and ignorance. Those who have
been to this realm can often find
themselves with some variation of the
cynical philosophical view [music] known
as misanthropy. A general dislike or
disdain for the human species as a
whole. With this view, the flaws and
vices of humankind, moral, intellectual,
and aesthetic, [music]
eclipse everything else about us. All
human beings are irredeemably faulty and
fickle, and society only serves to
reinforce, [music]
organize, and demonstrate our flaws at
scale. This view has been explicitly
[music] referenced or generally embodied
in the works of many prominent
philosophers throughout history. 17th
century English philosopher Thomas
Hobbes argued that humans are
fundamentally self-interested and
without the imposition of an absolute
sovereign like a monarch, our condition
reliably leads to violence [music] and
social breakdown. He writes, "So that in
the nature of man we find three
principal causes of quarrel. First
competition, secondly dissidence,
thirdly glory. The first maketh men
invade for gain, the second for safety,
and the third for reputation, the first
use violence to make themselves masters
of other men's persons, wives, children,
and cattle. The second to defend them,
the third for trifles.
On the opposite end of the misanthropic
spectrum, 17th century Genevan
philosopher Jeanjac Rouso argued that
humans are inherently good, but society
is a corruptive agent that causes us to
become vain, competitive, prideful, and
ultimately loathome. Though Rouso and
Hobbes disagree on how and when humanity
enters the misanthropic [music] lens,
they both ultimately arrive at a
similarly cynical view of humanity.
Other philosophers like Dioynes the
cynic, Arthur Schopenhau, and Emil
Chiron implicitly expressed misanthropic
[music]
views through philosophies that embraced
resignation from humanity or an
aestheticism of the self. Others have
expressed a kind of misanthropy through
their creative work. Writers like
Jonathan Swift, Charles Bakowski, and
Fernando Pasoa all engaged with the
humanity they rejected through their
creative work. Ultimately, whether one
fully agrees with the view or not, we
don't need to look too hard or too far
to at least understand some [music]
version of it. Humanity is pervaded by
vain celebrity culture, corrupt
political movements, vicious power
dynamics, everyday selfishness and
cruelty, the organization and
amplification of rage and hatred, the
immensity of injustice and inequality,
of famine and war, [music] of desire and
futility. We seem to so needlessly
continue an absurd persistent
destruction of ourselves and the world.
Whether that's our fault or the
underpinning of nature's [music] is hard
to say. Antiatalism.
Perhaps one of the darkest seeming
philosophies that misanthropy can lead
to is what is known as antiatalism. The
philosophical position that assigns a
negative value to human birth. Though
antiatalism is arguably the logical next
step after missanthropy, it has very
different foundations and implications.
What separates antiatalism from
misanthropic views is that it is an
ethical position. This is also what
separates it from individuals who choose
not to have children simply out of
personal preference. For the
antiatalist, the problem with
reproduction is moral. It relates to the
management and prevention of suffering.
South African philosopher David Benitar
is widely regarded as the leading
thinker associated with this philosophy.
In his book, Better Never to Have been,
published in 2006, he comprehensively
formalizes what have become some of the
most prominent arguments for the
philosophy. Benitar ultimately argues
that human or sentient existence is on
balance more negative than positive. The
often intense and regular experiences of
pain and [music] discomfort eclipse the
fleeting and frequent experiences of
pleasure and joy. Furthermore, Benitar
argues that things are actually much
worse than we are even aware of,
especially if we reject the notion that
existence has a net negative value.
Benitar claims we delude ourselves into
believing that our experience of
existence is better than it is. Partly
due to an evolutionary optimism bias
known as the Polyiana principle.
Research does in fact suggest that
pleasant experiences tend to be
remembered more readily and are often
weighted more heavily than unpleasant
ones, particularly at the subconscious
level. Though it should be noted that at
the conscious momentto moment level,
people often fixate on the negative even
though they evaluate their whole lives
as more positive. Regardless of any
biases, if we consider how often we are
in some form of discomfort or pain in
life, it likely does appear to overtake
how often we are in states of definitive
joy or pleasure. Even in the best cases,
[music] individuals who are wealthy,
have good family and friends, do work
they find meaningful and so on. [music]
They too will experience intense regular
unrequitted purposeless suffering. No
one escapes the pain of hot and cold,
hunger and urine, anxiety and boredom,
the aches of a body that fills and
empties, cramps and breaks, grows and
decays, the loss of all that one loves,
the disqu of the uncertainty above and
beneath all things.
With this, Benitar concludes that it is
better to never be and it is morally
wrong to bring sentient beings into
existence. A common and reasonable
counter-argument here is that even if
less frequent or less intense, the
experience and remembrance of joy,
pleasure, love, meaning, and wonder can
make our existence worth it. These
qualities do enough work to justify the
pain and [music] suffering. And so, by
not bringing humans into existence, such
joys, pleasures, wonders, and meanings
are missed out on. For Benitar, however,
it is not all worth it. In what is known
as his asymmetry argument, he attempts
to refute this rebuttal by showcasing
the asymmetry of pleasure and pain. His
argument is divided into the following
four claims. The presence of pleasure is
good. The presence of pain is bad. The
absence of pain is good. And the absence
of pleasure is neutral. Neither good nor
bad so long as there is no individual
being deprived of it. With this, Benitar
concludes that the presence of pleasure
cannot compensate for the presence of
pain in the moral evaluation of birth
because the absence of pain is good even
when no one exists. Whereas the absence
of pleasure is not [music] bad so long
as there is no one being deprived of it.
This might sound bizarre, wrong, or
counterintuitive at first, [music] and
that's fair. Perhaps it is. But Benitar
defends it with several compelling
thought experiments. For example,
consider the planet Mars. Right now, no
one exists there. [music] Strictly in
the moral sense, is that bad? Is it
morally wrong that there are no sentient
beings on [music] Mars experiencing joy
or pleasure? Arguably, no. It seems to
be neutral. Alternatively, however, what
if there were a civilization of sentient
beings experiencing constant pain and
suffering? That would seem to [music] be
quite bad. There lies the asymmetry for
Benitar. He writes, "Whereas at least
when we think of them, we rightly are
sad for inhabitants of a foreign land
whose lives are characterized by
suffering, when we hear that some island
is unpopulated, we are not similarly sad
[music] for the happy people who, had
they existed, would have populated this
island. Similarly, nobody really mourns
for those who do not exist on Mars,
feeling sorry for potential such beings
that they cannot [music] enjoy life.
Yet, if we knew that there were sentient
life on Mars, but that Martians were
suffering, we would regret this [music]
for them. The fact that we would regret
the suffering within their life is
sufficient to support the asymmetry that
I am defending. [music] The point is
that we regret suffering but not the
absent pleasures of those who could have
existed.
Of course, on the contrary, one could
argue that it is some amount bad that an
island or planet is [music] desolate
without any sentient experience. If we
took it to the extreme and removed all
life from every island, continent,
[music] planet, and place in the cosmos,
leaving an unending space devoid of any
life, consciousness, awareness, joy,
meaning, love, or possibility that does
arguably elicit a terrible [music] sense
of regret. There are also other
legitimate, well-reasoned arguments
against antiatalism. [music]
From a normative, metaethical
standpoint, why is it moral to
prioritize the elimination of suffering,
even if it's asymmetrically [music]
experienced in relation to pleasure? Why
should it be a prioritization to
eliminate suffering's predominance over
all else? Is this not a preferential
subjective claim? Can we truly say that
the absence [music] of pain is morally
better than the absence of pleasure?
What objective truth is that rooted in?
Is this stance not like all stances
located in the bogggy grounds of
assumptions [music] and intuitions?
Beyond Benitar, there are also many
other philosophers and thinkers [music]
who have shared similar antiatalist
sentiments from pessimist philosophers
like Schopenhau, Chiron and Peter Vessel
Zapa to writers like Thomas Legatti and
Samuel Beckett. However, [music] an
important thing to consider and keep in
mind with these individuals and their
ideas here including Benitars is that
they are not expressing purely
misanthropic views. [music] They are not
promoting a destructive idea for the
sake of destruction. It is not
inherently a disdain for humanity, but a
pity and compassion. Schopenhau writes,
"If children were brought into the world
by an act of pure reason alone, would
the human race continue to exist? Would
not a man rather have so much sympathy
with the coming generation as to spare
at the burden of existence? Or at any
rate, not take it upon himself to impose
that burden upon it in cold blood?" For
most of these individuals, this
philosophy is not a matter of destroying
the human race. It is a matter of
liberating it.
However, the problem here is this.
[music] Let's say antiatalism could and
were to be accepted as the morally and
objectively right view and humanity
somehow phased itself out of existence.
There is absolutely no reason to believe
that life would not continue in other
forms and continue to evolve into other
forms including intelligent and sentient
life. What then? Suffering in new
potentially worse forms. [music]
Humanity cannot extinguish the fire it
was forged out of by letting itself be
burned up in it. [music]
Existence is suffering. Every being is
combustible in its flames [music] as it
spreads, burns, clears, and replenishes
reality. Humanity is just the only
current species that is self agrandizing
enough to think that with the [music]
extinction of itself, all would be made
well in the world. Then nature would be
purged of nature. [music] Surely, human
life is unique, and thus human life is
uniquely treacherous. We see and feel
everything acutely. [music] And so the
fire that is existence inflicts us
greatly. But it also fuels us greatly.
[music] Its combustion fuels us to come
up with ideas and philosophies not to
destroy but to relieve, to improve, to
transcend. [music]
Even if that means considering the idea
of voluntary extinction.
Regardless of whether one agrees with
the arguments laid forth by antiatalism,
regardless of whether one sees humanity
as gross, contemptable, beautiful,
allinsspiring, or all the above, one
cannot deny how remarkable it is that
[music] a species can create and
consider such ideas. That it can see and
pity its and others pain, and it can
work to reduce such pain, defining new
moralities and striving toward better
realities.
Though perhaps if we could return to
that zygote we once were and could
decide whether our legs, arms, torso,
and head came out, we might decide
against it. Of course, we cannot do
this. We cannot [music] and do not
choose to be here. Nothing does. But we
are here both individually and
collectively. We feel we are separate
from all that contains us. Like we can
deny our existence [music] and its
nature, but we are still formless in the
womb of reality, constrained by and
dependent on it. Our borders are not
real. [music] They are imagined. We
cannot reason our way out of the order
and chaos of nature. We cannot escape or
revise it. Not through continuation, not
through extinguishment. Life will always
strive, and striving will always be
painful and grotesque. Humanity cannot
stop that, but it can participate in it.
And it can strive [music] to strive for
good reasons, to love itself in all its
flaws, and to see the meaning and
rationality of the absurdity.
One of humanity's most profound
qualities is its ability not only to
endure the difficulties of existence,
but to create and share [music] reasons
for and out of this endurance.
Remarkable ideas, insights, and
expressions have accumulated in the
libraries of history, [music] in books,
research, and media that help us better
understand and deal with ourselves and
the world. That's why this video
sponsor, Short Form, is so genuinely
useful. Short Form produces highquality
[music] guides and analytical summaries
of non-fiction books in both written and
audio form, making it so that you can
tap into the world's knowledge and ideas
efficiently and effectively. Unlike many
summary apps which are often brief,
simplistic or AI generated, short form
doesn't just summarize. It has an actual
team of writers and editors who curate
and break down books ideas chapter by
chapter, adding commentary and analysis,
connecting them to thinkers and
including exercises to help [music] the
idea stick. This is especially valuable
for complex or dense books like
Friedrich Nichzche's thus spoke. [music]
Having a clear conceptual map before
reading the book, or having a structured
way to reflect on it afterward
completely changes how much you can take
away from it. I use short form to help
discover new books, prime my
understanding before reading the
complete works, or to revisit books I've
already read for refreshers. Whether
you're interested in philosophy,
science, health, finance, or essentially
any subject, Short Form opens up a kind
of modern library, curated, vast, yet
accessible and useful. For about the
cost of one book a month, you get access
[music] to this entire library of
thousands. Get a free trial and $50 off
the annual plan at shortform.com/pursuit
[music] or by using my link in the
description.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general. And see
you next video.